so in the last video I introduced my
staircase plan for explaining Spinners
which starts with the simplest
explanations at the bottom and ends with
the most complicated explanations at the
top we're going to start at the bottom
of the staircase which is basic examples
of spinners in physics
in the next four or five videos I'm
going to talk about two examples of how
Spinners come up in physics the
polarization of light waves and Quantum
spin States
we're going to find that both of these
phenomena can be described by Spinners
in the form of two by one columns with
complex number entries
afterward we'll see how we can visualize
these Spinners as flag poles on a sphere
called the plank array sphere or block
sphere
in this video we're going to discuss all
the different polarizations of light
waves and their corresponding Spinners
which are called Jones vectors in this
specific case
and in the next video we will discuss
how to rotate between these
polarizations using su2 matrices
so I'm hoping you're familiar with
electric and magnetic fields the
electric field is a set of vectors
everywhere in space that point in the
direction that a positive charge will be
pulled in due to electric forces
the magnetic field is another set of
vectors everywhere in space that tell us
which direction a compass will point due
to Magnetic forces
according to the laws of electricity and
magnetism it's possible for electric and
magnetic field vectors to vibrate back
and forth together in a wave called an
electromagnetic wave
the light we see is an example of
electromagnetic waves
usually electromagnetic waves are
traveling waves meaning they travel
through space over time
the image you're seeing here is a
snapshot of an electromagnetic wave at a
single instant in time but as time
passes by the wave will travel forward
electromagnetic waves are transverse
waves this means the direction of the
wave oscillations is always
perpendicular to the direction of travel
so if an electromagnetic wave is
traveling in the Z direction the wave
can oscillate in the X Y plane
perpendicular to the direction of travel
but the wave cannot oscillate in the Z
Direction parallel to the direction of
travel
the polarization of a given
electromagnetic wave is the geometric
orientation of the wave
we only use the electric field e to
define the polarization of an
electromagnetic wave so we ignore the
magnetic field when talking about
polarization
let's look at an electromagnetic wave
propagating in the Z direction again
here we're looking at a snapshot of a
traveling wave at one instant in time
when the electric field oscillates up
and down along the y-axis we call this
vertical polarization
if we rotate this Wave by a quarter turn
it is now oscillating left and right
along the x-axis and we call this
horizontal polarization
if we rotate the wave by another quarter
turn we end up with vertical
polarization again although with the
wave shifted by a half cycle compared to
the original wave
let's look more closely at a vertically
polarized wave remember the electric
field is a vector field meaning it is
represented as an arrow at every point
in space and time
the arrow has components in the X Y and
Z directions which we can write like
this using a linear combination of the
XYZ basis vectors
we can also write this as a three
component column like this
for a vertically polarized wave the
electric field only exists along the
y-axis so the x and z components of the
electric field go to zero
if we were to write out the Y component
of the electric field for this traveling
wave it would be an amplitude a times a
cosine wave that depends on both time
and space
here T is time and Z is the location
along the z-axis
Omega is the angular frequency and K is
the angular wave number
I find traveling waves are easiest to
visualize on a space-time diagram with
time moving into the future as we move
upward
let's say that we have a wave that
travels in the positive Z Direction over
time
we could draw out this traveling wave as
a surface in our space-time diagram
the density of the waves in the spatial
direction is given by the wave number
and the density of the waves in time is
given by the frequency
one thing we can do to modify our
traveling wave is to add an extra Phi
value inside the sinusoid function you
can think of this as indicating the
wave's starting value at the origin Z
equals zero when time T equals zero
this starting value is called a phase
and changing the phase value will shift
the wave back and forth along the axis
of travel
applying a phase shift of negative pi
over 2 to a cosine will shift the way
the head a quarter cycle which is
equivalent to a sine wave
now something that can help us represent
waves is remembering Euler's formula
which tells us that we can write e to
the power of the imaginary I times Theta
as cosine theta plus I times sine Theta
this is a useful property because if we
have e to the I Theta and we want to add
some angle Phi to it all we do is just
multiply by e to the I times Phi and use
the standard exponent rules to rewrite
this as a single exponential with the
exponents added
if we then use Euler's formula to
convert back to sine and cosine we see
that a phase Phi has been added inside
the sinusoid functions
now electromagnetic waves are described
by real numbers but for convenience we
can pretend that our ey component is
actually a complex number where the real
part of this complex number is the
actual electric field we observe in real
life with the imaginary part being
ignored
this means the full ey component would
have a real part with a cosine wave and
we can invent the fake imaginary part to
be a sine wave since we ignore it anyway
using Euler's formula we can write this
more compactly as a complex exponential
this also means we can pull the phase
Phi out using exponent rules and write
it as a multiplicative Factor e to the I
Phi
this allows us to write traveling waves
as three separate multiplicative factors
the amplitude times the phase times the
actual traveling wave
so while the true electric field here is
just the real part of this complex wave
we can write the electric Fields using
complex exponentials for mathematical
convenience
as I said before if we take this
vertically polarized wave and rotate it
a quarter turn we get a horizontally
polarized wave
in this case the wave only oscillates in
the X Direction and so the Y and Z
components of the field are zero
once again the true electric field is
given by a cosine but for convenience we
can write it as a complex exponential
with the amplitude and phase written
separately in front
so to review with the vertically
polarized waves the Y component of the
electric field is a traveling wave and
the xnz components are zero and with a
horizontally polarized wave the X
component of the electric field is a
traveling wave and the ynz components
are zero
now we know from physical experiments
that electromagnetic waves can be
superimposed on top of each other so
it's possible to add horizontally and
vertically polarized waves together like
this
now notice that the two polarizations
each have their own amplitude and their
own phase but the actual traveling wave
portion is identical in both so we can
Factor it out and write it outside the
column like this
now here I want to State the main idea
of this video when it comes to studying
the polarizations of waves all the
information we need to look at is
contained inside this column the
amplitudes and the phases
the actual traveling wave portion of the
formula can be ignored since it's the
same for all components
we can even go one step further and
ignore the Z component altogether since
we can always choose coordinates where
the Z direction is the direction of wave
propagation and therefore the Z
component of the electric field will
always be zero
the resulting two by one column of
complex numbers is called a Jones vector
and it tells us everything we need to
know about the polarization of a given
wave
any light wave polarization can be
written as a linear combination of a
horizontally polarized wave and a
vertically polarized wave each with
complex numbers in front denoting their
respective amplitudes and phases
moving forward I'm going to write this
horizontally polarized wave of amplitude
1 using the vector Capital H
and I'll write this vertically polarized
wave with amplitude 1 using the vector
capital V
so using the idea of Jones vectors we
can create new polarizations by
selecting different values for the
amplitude and phase parameters
for example we can set both phases to
zero so that the horizontal and vertical
polarizations are in Phase with each
other and then set both amplitudes to
one
if we think of H as a vector along the
x-axis and v as a vector along the
y-axis this new Jones Vector points
diagonally to the upper right this is
called diagonal polarization denoted
with a capital D
this is what we would get if we took a
horizontally polarized wave and rotated
it counterclockwise by 45 degrees
although according to Pythagoras the
Jones Vector h plus V has an amplitude
of the square root of 2. so we usually
divide the components by the square root
of 2 to force the amplitude of D to be
one
it's also possible to set the amplitude
to plus one for H and negative 1 for V
and this gives us another polarization
that points to the lower right
we call this anti-diagonal polarization
a
this is what we would get if we took a
horizontally polarized wave and rotated
it clockwise by 45 degrees
once again we normalize this by dividing
by the square root of two
so we can get the D and a polarizations
by adding H and V together in the right
amounts
in fact we can make the waves
polarization have any angle on this
circle if we set the coefficients in
front of H and V properly
but there are actually more
polarizations that we still haven't seen
yet
let's again set both amplitudes to one
and set the horizontal phase to be zero
and set the vertical phase to be pi over
2 which is a phase of a quarter wave
cycle
this polarization is more difficult to
visualize so let's bring back our column
notation with the traveling wave to
understand it better
Let's Pretend We're stuck at the
position Z equals zero and the angular
frequency of the wave is one and we're
watching The Wave travel around the X Y
plane over time
what would this look like
we can combine the exponentials then use
Euler's formula and then take the real
part to see that the electric field is
given by a cosine and a cosine with a
phase factor of a quarter cycle which is
really the same thing as a negative sign
at time equals zero this gives the
coordinates one zero then at T equals pi
over two we get the coordinates zero
negative one
then at T equals Pi we get negative one
zero
at T equals three pi over two we get
zero one and at T equals two Pi we get
one zero again
so in this wave the electric field
Vector travels around in a circle in a
clockwise Direction over time
bringing back the z-axis if we take our
left hand and point our Thumb in the
direction of wave travel along the
z-axis the electric field Vector at the
origin Z equals zero will follow the
direction of our curled fingers
since the wave follows a circle
according to our left hand we call it
left circular polarized
this wave would have a helix shape in
three dimensions
Wikipedia user Dave 3457 has made a
great animation of this that he's put
into the public domain
we denote left circular polarized waves
as capital l
it's also more common to write e to the
I pi over 2 as just I which is a quarter
turn in the complex plane
and once again we normalize by dividing
by the square root of 2.
if we repeat this process from the start
but instead giving the vertical
polarization a phase of negative pi over
2 we get a helix wave that corkscrews in
the opposite direction matching our
right hand when the right thumb points
in the direction of wave travel
so we call this right circular polarized
denoted by capital r
now you'll notice in this video I've
written my traveling waves with a
positive time term and a negative Z term
some textbooks use the opposite sign
convention with a positive Z term and a
negative time term and as a result the
Jones vectors for circularly polarized
waves have opposite signs on the
imaginary parts
so make sure you know which sign
convention you're using when talking
about circularly polarized waves
so to summarize this video we initially
discovered the Jones vectors H and V
which represent horizontally and
vertically polarized traveling waves we
then found that writing them in
different linear combinations could give
us new polarizations of light like
diagonal and anti-diagonal polarizations
and the left and right circular
polarizations
we're going to see in the next video
that these Jones vectors that represent
wave polarizations are actually spinners
at this point there's no particular
reason why we would decide these pairs
of complex numbers are special objects
that deserve the special name of spinner
but in the next video we're going to see
how we can rotate these various
polarizations into each other using
special matrices called su2 matrices
and this will reveal a special angle
doubling relationship between physical
space and the space of wave
polarizations we'll see that one
rotation in physical space corresponds
to two full rotations in the
polarization space
the Jones vectors that live in
polarization space require two full
rotations to get back to the starting
point and this is exactly what we would
expect from spinners
in the meantime before the next video
I'd suggest trying to draw out the
shapes of various polarizations for the
Jones vectors shown on the screen here
if you feel confused just use the
strategy I showed earlier of taking Z
equals zero and Omega equals one and
plugging in different time values to see
how the wave moves around in the X Y
plane
the answers are linked in the
description